National Women's Trade Union League of America Records on Microfilm 5709 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Women's Trade Union League of America Records on Microfilm
1903-1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Women's Trade Union League
5709 mf
2.78 cubic feet
25 microfilm reels
These records include correspondence, reports, speeches, notes, printed matter, minutes of meetings, proceedings of the League and of the International Congress of Working Women, biographical material on the League's officers, and correspondence between the National League and its local branches. Major issues covered include the eight-hour day, minimum wage, establishment of sanitary work areas, federal aid to education, civil rights, price controls and social security.
3833878
Biographical / Historical
As the League's president from 1907 to 1922, Margaret Dreier Robins, the well-to-do daughter of a Brooklyn businessman, guided it through the period of its most active work. Among her close associates were several working class women who served as officers of the national or local Leagues, including Leonora O'Reilly of New York and Agnes Nestor and Mary Anderson of Chicago. After 1922, working women took over the leadership; Rose Schneiderman, a veteran leader of strikes in the needle trades, served as national president from 1926 to 1950.
Biographical / Historical
The Women's Trade Union League was founded in 1903 during the annual convention of the American Federation of Labor. Local branches were organized within a year in Boston, Chicago and New York. In 1907 its name became the National Women's Trade Union League of America. The League sought to counter the exploitation of working women by organizing them into trade unions and by securing protective legislation regulating their hours and working conditions and setting minimum wage standards. Its dual membership of working and middle class women made the League unique among social reform organizations of its day.
Scope and Contents
The records of the National Women's Trade Union League of America (NWTUL) span the lifetime of the organization from the first meeting in Boston in 1903 to the last bulletin of its official organ, LIFE AND LABOR, announcing the termination of the League's national charter in 1950. The records consist of correspondence, memoranda, speeches, clippings, notes, printed matter, and miscellaneous other items.
The NWTUL's administrative operations are well documented in the headquarters records. Its policies and activities are recorded in the minutes of the Executive Board meetings and in the correspondence. Most of the letters and memoranda are from the various national League secretaries, particularly Elisabeth Christman, who held the position from 1921 to 1950. There is, as well, correspondence from various members of both the national and local Leagues, especially from the New York, Boston, and Chicago branches. Many of the local League members also served as officers and/or Executive Board members of the national League and are represented in the headquarters records. Included in this group are Margaret Dreier Robins, Mary Morton Kehew, Jane Addams, Rose Schneiderman, Mary Kenney O'Sullivan, Melinda Scott, Agnes Nestor, and Mary E. Dreier. Interspersed with the materials documenting the activities of the League are financial statements enumerating sources of income and costs of operation.
The subject files as well as the headquarters records offer a major source of information concerning the League's goal of organizing women wage workers into trade unions. There is considerable material on the early history of the League in the historical data file. Many of the files on individual members contain biographical information, and the file on the American Federation of Labor sheds light on the League's relationship to that organization. Here and in the headquarters records is correspondence with Samuel Gompers, Frank Morrison, Frank Duffy, and Florence C. Thorne.
Both series (headquarters records and subject files) contain documentation of the League's efforts to improve women's working conditions through supporting strikes, particularly in the garment industry, through the use of a training school to develop leadership among women of the working class, and through lobbying for the enactment of protective labor legislation. Issues such as the eight-hour day, a minimum wage, and the establishment of sanitary work areas were the focus of the League's early days. However, its interests broadened in later years to include federal aid to education, civil rights, price control, and social security. Correspondents include Ethel M. Smith, Eleanor Roosevelt, Sophonisba P. Breckinridge, Mary Anderson, Alice Henry, and Frances Perkins.
The records of the NWTUL also contain proceedings for 10 of the 13 national conventions and mimeographed corrected copies of the proceedings of the three international congresses which the League sponsored.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5690 mf: Women's Trade Union League Papers on Microfilm
Civil rights -- United States; Eight-hour movement; Federal aid to education -- United States; Hours of labor -- Law and legislation -- United States; Industrial hygiene -- Law and legislation -- United States; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; Social security--United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- Clothing industry -- United States; Labor leaders -- United States; Wage-price policy -- United States; Wages -- Law and legislation -- United States; Minimum wage -- Law and legislation -- United States; Wages -- Women -- Law and legislation -- United States; Women labor union members -- United States; Women social reformers -- United States; Women -- Employment -- Law and legislation -- United States; Women -- Working conditions -- United States; Workers' education -- Women -- United States; Working class women -- United States; Working conditions -- Law and legislation -- United States; Addams, Jane. 1860-1935.; Anderson, Mary, 1872-1964.; Breckinridge, Sophonisba Preston, 1866-1948.; Christman, Elisabeth.; Dreier, Mary E.; Duffy, Frank, 1861-1955.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Henry, Alice, 1957-1943; Kehew, Mary Morton.; Morrison, Frank, 1859-1949; Nestor, Agnes, 1880-1948.; O'Sullivan, Mary Kenney, 1864-1943.; Perkins, Frances, 1882-1965.; Robins, Margaret Dreier.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Schneiderman, Rose, 1882-; Scott, Melinda.; Smith, Ethel M.; Thorne, Florence Calvert.; American Federation of Labor; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; National Women's Trade Union League of America; Women's Trade Union League of Boston; Women's Trade Union League of Chicago; Women's Trade Union League of New York
3833878
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1903-1914 (Reel 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Principal subject index 1903-14
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1915-1922 (Reel 2, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index 1915-22
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1923-1925 (Reel 3, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index 1923-1925
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1926-1929 (Reel 4, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index 1926- Apr 1929
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1929-1932 (Reel 5, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index May 1929-Apr. 1932
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1932-1935 (Reel 6, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index May 1932-35
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1936-1938 (Reel 7, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index 1936-38
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1939-1941 (Reel 7, Folder 2)
  Principal subject index 1939-41
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1939-1941 (Reel 8, Folder 1)
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1942-1945 (Reel 8, Folder 2)
  Principal subject index 1942-45
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1942-1945 (Reel 9, Folder 1)
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1946-1948 (Reel 9, Folder 2)
  Principal subject index 1946- Apr 1948
- Headquarters Records, 1903-1950, 1948-1950 (Reel 10, Folder 1)
  Principal subject index May 1948-June 1950
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 10, Folder 2)
  Aderton, Aileen, 1949-50. American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1949-50. American Federation of Labor, 1915-33 and undated. Auxiliaries, 1941-49 and undated. Brock, Mrs. Eugene J. (H. Rose), 1925-50 and undated. Burling, Mrs. Edward B. (Louise B.), 1925-50 and undated. Christman, Elisabeth, 1918-50. Corbett, Maude B., 1925-50. Deuser, Marion Burns, 1948. Dowd, Mollie, 1935. Dreier, Mary E., 1941 and 1948. E miscellaneous, 1948-49. Economic Cooperation Act, 1948-50. Education - Citizens Federal Committee on Education, 1949-50. - Federal aid to education, 1949-50 and undated. - Office worker's summer school, 1935, 1940, 1949-50. Equal Pay, 1947-50.
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 11, Folder 1)
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 12, Folder 1)
  Executive Board - General, 1935, 1948-50. - Dueser, Marion Burns, 1948-49. - Dreier, Mary E., 1949-50. - Newman, Pauline M., 1948-50 and undated. - Winslow, Mary N., 1948-49. F miscellaneous, 1948-49. Fair Employment Practices Commission, 1949. Fair Labor Standards Act, 1949-50. Foreign-correspondence - General, 1949-50 - Australia, 1949-50. - Czechoslovakia, 1950. - France, 1949. - Germany, 1948-50 and undated.
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 13, Folder 1)
  Foreign-correspondence - Great Britain, 1949-50 - Hungary, 1950 - India, 1950 - Japan, 1949 - Sweden, 1949-50 Greenwood, Elma L., 1949-50. Health insurance, 1949-50. Higgins, Mrs. William H. (Elsie Herrick), 1947-50. Hospital Council, 1947-49 and undated. Hours of labor for women, 1913-32 and undated. Ingersoll, Mrs. Raymond V. (Marion C.), 1923-50. Inter-American Commission of Women, 1948-50. Inter-American program, Women's Bureau, U.S. Dept. of Labor - Women leaders visit United States, 1948-49. International Congress (later Federation) of Working Women - General, 1918-21
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 14, Folder 1)
  International Congress (later Federation of Working Women - General, 1923-27 and undated - South American countries, 1921-24 and undated International Labour Organization - General 1948-50 - Committee for the United States, 1947-50 Legislation - Atlantic Pact, 1949 - Atomic energy, 1947-50 - Civil Rights, 1949-50 - Displaced persons, 1949-50 and undated - Economic Expansion Act of 1949, 1949-50 - Equal rights --- General, 1921-50 and undated --- Records of Congressmen, 1944-49
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 14, Folder 2)
  Legislation - Extension of labor education, 1949-50 - Government reorganization (Hoover Commission), 1949-50 - International relations, 1949-50 - Lobby Acr, 1946-50 and undated - Mundt-Nixon bill, 1948-50 - Poll tax, 1946-49 - Price control, 1947-48 Local leagues - Bloomington-Normal, Bloomington, Ill., 1947-50 - Boston, Mass., 1946-50 - Chicago, Ill., 1949-50 - Constitutions, 1935-49 and undated - District of Columbia, 1947-40
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 15, Folder 1)
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 15, Folder 2)
  Local Leagues - Illinois State, 1947-50 - Kansas City, Mo., 1944-50 - Kelso-Longview, Longview Wash., 1944-1949 - Milwaukee, Wis., 1948-50 and undated - New York, N.Y., 1949-50 - Notices to, 1947-50 - Officers and meeting nights, 1949-50
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 16, Folder 1)
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 16, Folder 2)
  Local leagues - Racine, Wis., 1945-50 - St. Louis, Mo., 1948-50 - Seattle, Wash., 1945-50 - Suggested programs, 1930-32 and undated - Toledo, Ohio, 1947-50 - Worcester, Mass., 1947-50 Minimum wage, 1913-35 and undated. National Citizens Council for Migrant Labor, 1948-50. National Women's Trade Union League of America - Attacks on, 1925-31 and undated
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1948 (Reel 17, Folder 1)
  Historical data, 1903-48 and undated
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 18, Folder 1)
  Publicity, 1924-50 and undated. Nestor, Agnes, 1914-49. Newman, Pauline M., 1945. Robins, Margaret Dreier, 1911-45 and undated. Schneiderman, Rose, 1928-48 and undated. Shop investigations, undated. Social security, 1948-50. Stone, Margaret F., undated. Taft-Hartley Act, 1949. Trade agreements, 1949. Trade unions (women in) 1913-42
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 18, Folder 2)
  Trade unions (women in) 1943-50 and undated. Union shop, 1911-24 and undated. United Nations (American Association for the United Nations), 1948-50. U.S. Employment Service (Federal Advisory Council for), 1946-49. Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1924-27. Winslow, Mary N., 1927-48. Women on policy-making commissions, 1942-49. Women's Bureau, 1916-50 and undated. Women's Conference on International Affairs, 1947-49. Women's status, 1948-50 and undated
- Subject File, ca. 1903-50 and undated, 1903-1950 (Reel 19, Folder 1)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1909-1911 (Reel 19, Folder 2)
  Proceedings - Sept. 27-Oct. 2, 1909 (Chicago, Ill.) - June 12-19, 1911 (Boston, Mass.)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1909-1911 (Reel 20, Folder 1)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1913-1915 (Reel 20, Folder 2)
  Proceedings - June 2-7, 1913 (St. Louis, Mo.) - June 7-12, 1915 (New York, N.Y.)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1913-1915 (Reel 21, Folder 1)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1919-1922 (Reel 21, Folder 2)
  Proceedings - June 2-7, 1919 (Philadelphia, Pa.) - June 5-10, 1922 (Waukegan, Ill.)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1919-1922 (Reel 22, Folder 1)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1924-1929 (Reel 23, Folder 1)
  Proceedings - June 16-21, 1924 (New York, N.Y.) - May 6-11, 1929 (District of Columbia)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1924-1929 (Reel 24, Folder 1)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1936-1947 (Reel 24, Folder 2)
  Proceedings - May 4-9, 1936 (District of Columbia) - May 19-22, 1947 (District of Columbia)
- National Conventions, 1909-47, 1936-1947 (Reel 25, Folder 1)
- International Congress (Later Federation) of Working Women, 1919-23 (Reel 25, Folder 2)
  Oct.28-Nov. 6, 1919 (District of Columbia) - Proceedings
- International Congress (Later Federation) of Working Women, 1919-23, 1921-1923 (Reel 25, Folder 3)
  Oct. 17-24, 1921 (Geneva, Switzerland) - Proceedings - Delegates - Recommendations of constitutional commission - Resolution on disarmament - Summary of proceedings Aug. 14-18, 1923 (Vienna, Austria) - Report of proceedings - International Federation of Working Women; Report Presented by the Secretariat at the Biennial Congress August 14th-18th 1923, Held at Schonbrunn Castle, Vienna, November 1921 to July 1923 - Working Women in Many Countries; Report of Congress Held at Vienna, August 1923 (Amsterdam, International Federation of Trade Unions.)